Exercise 4-7, Rule 4, held T before N. The held T is, strictly speaking, not really a
T at all. Remember, T and N are very close in the mouth. If you have an N immediately
after a T, you don't pop the T. The tongue is in the T position, but you release the
air with the N, not the T. There's no T and no schwa. Make a special point of not
letting your tongue release from the top of your mouth before you drop into the NN.
Otherwise, button would sound like two words, button. An unstressed T or double T
followed by N is held. Read the following words and sentences out loud. Make sure
that the blue T's are held. Remember, there is no uh sound before the N. Note,
another point to remember is that you need a sharp upward sliding intonation, up to
the held T, then a quick drop for the N. Just go to the T position and hum.
Written, written, sentence, forgotten, certain, curtain, mitten, Martin, bitten,
button, kitten, mutant, latent, mountain, recently, lately, partly, frequently. One,
he's forgotten the carton of satin mittens. Two, she's certain that he has
written it. Three, the cotton curtain is not in the fountain. Four, the hikers went
in the mountains. Five, Martin has gotten a kitten. Six, students study Latin in
Britain. Seven, Whitney has a patent on those sentences. Eight, he has not
forgotten what was written about the mutant on the mountain. Nine, it's not
certain that it was gotten from the fountain. Ten, you need to put an orange
cotton curtain on that window. Eleven, we that certain satin better than the carton
of cotton curtains. 12. The Intercontinental Hotel is in Seattle. 13.
The frightened witness had forgotten the important written message. 14. The child
wasn't beaten because he had bitten the button.